<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Mary-le-Bow, before the Lord Mayor, Court of Aldermen and citizens of London on Wednesday, the 16th of September, a day appointed by Their Majesties for a solemn monthly fast / by Lilly Butler, Rector of Bubbingworth in Essex.</title>
            <author>Butler, Lilly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6278A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35817</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15564325</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15564325</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103781</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30728)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103781)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1588:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Mary-le-Bow, before the Lord Mayor, Court of Aldermen and citizens of London on Wednesday, the 16th of September, a day appointed by Their Majesties for a solemn monthly fast / by Lilly Butler, Rector of Bubbingworth in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Butler, Lilly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCI [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LVII, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:103781:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TLER</hi>'s Faſt-SERMON Preached before the Lord Mayor, AND <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT</hi> of <hi>ALDERMEN, Sept.</hi> 16. 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:103781:2"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Pilkington Mayor </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Jovis xvii<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> die Septembris 1691. Annoque Regni Regis &amp; Reginae Willielmi &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae Angliae, &amp;c. Tertio.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe are to deſire Mr. <hi>Lilly Butler</hi> to Print his Sermon, preached yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>St. Mary Le Bow,</hi> before the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Liveries of the ſeveral Companies of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Goodfellow.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103781:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at St. Mary-le-Bow, Before the Lord Mayor, COURT of ALDERMEN, AND CITIZENS of <hi>LONDON,</hi> On <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> a day appointed by their Majeſties for a ſolemn Monthly Faſt. By <hi>Lilly Butler,</hi> Rector of <hi>Bubbingworth</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick-lane.</hi> M DC XCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103781:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103781:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">R</hi> Tho. Pilkington, Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London,</hi> AND THE COURT of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Know not any thing could move you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Printing this plain Sermon, but a great affection to the deſign of it: Which I pray God increaſe in you all, and make you ſignally inſtrumental in promoting that Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, wherein the ſafety and happineſs of our Country is ſo highly concerned. And if the publiſhing of this diſcourſe may confer but any
<pb facs="tcp:103781:4"/> little matter towards it, whatever other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects may be found in it (eſpecially after ſo kind and favourable an acceptance from you) will not much concern</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Humble and Obedient Servant,</hi> L. Butler.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103781:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Iſaiah LVII 21.</bibl> There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Prophet towards the beginning of this Chapter, upbraideth the <hi>Jews</hi> with their abominable wickedneſs and Idolatry; for which they were ſhortly to be made Captives in a <hi>ſtrange land.</hi> From whence, he telleth them, they ſhould in vain expect to be delivered, by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whoſe Gods they worſhipped, and with whoſe wickedneſs they had complied. <hi>V. 13. When thou crieſt let thy companions deliver thee: but the wind ſhall carry them all away; vanity ſhall take them.</hi> Nevertheleſs, if they ſhould at length <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think themſelves, in the land whither they were carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed captive,</hi> heartily bewail their ſins, and turn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, they ſhould again ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in proſperity, and peace upon <hi>Iſrael. But he that putteth his truſt in me,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>ſhall poſſeſs the land, and ſhall inherit my holy mountain.</hi> All things ſhall be made ready for a happy return. <hi>V.</hi> 14.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103781:5"/> 
               <hi>Caſt ye up, caſt ye up, take up the ſtumbling block out of the way of my people. The high and lofty one will revive the humble and contrite Spirits. v. 15. For I will not contend for ever,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>v. 16. neither will I be always wroth. For the iniquity of his covetouſneſs was I wroth, and ſmote him; I hid me and was wroth; I have ſeen his ways, v.</hi> 18. I have ſeen them at length corrected and reformed, therefore <hi>I will heal him; I will lead him alſo, and reſtore comforts to him, and to his mourners.</hi> Their mouths ſhall be filled with Praiſe and Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the reſtoration of their peace. <hi>I create the Fruit of the Lips; Peace, Peace to him that is far off, and to him that is near, ſaith the Lord, and I will heal him.</hi> But if upon their return out of Captivity, they ſhould forget their Redeemer, and return to their former wickedneſs; their Peace and Proſperity would ſoon be diſturbed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. For ſaith the Prophet, <hi>the wicked are like the troubled Sea, when it cannot reſt,</hi> which he explaineth in the words of the Text, and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the Teſtimony of his God that ſent him; <hi>there is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the <hi>wicked</hi> in this place, we are chiefly to underſtand, a wicked Nation or People, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainly by the account I have given of the context. And by <hi>peace,</hi> Proſperity and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in general; according to the common uſe of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103781:5"/> uſe of the word <hi>peace</hi> in the old Teſtament. The meaning of the words then may be expreſſed in in this plain Propoſition. That prevailing wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is moſt certainly deſtructive of the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and happineſs of a People. In diſcourſing upon which, I ſhall endeavour to do theſe Four things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To clear and manifeſt the truth of this propoſition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To ſhew that we of this Nation, are very much concerned in the Truth of it, and that it <hi>propheſieth evil concerning us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, To ſhew what is to be done by us, in order to the preventing this evil. And</p>
            <p>Fourthly, By ſome proper motives and argu- to perſwade every one to do his own part in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall endeavour to clear and manifeſt the Truth of this propoſition: That prevailing wickedneſs is moſt certainly deſtructive of the proſperity and happineſs of a people. This will be ſufficiently manifeſt by the conſideration of theſe following things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The abounding of iniquity is it ſelf the the great unhappineſs of a People. So long as a Nation is diſtempered with vice, <hi>the head ſick, and the heart faint, full of wounds, and bruiſes, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying ſores,</hi> as the Prophet deſcribeth <hi>a People laden with iniquity,</hi> no outward Priviledges or Advantages can make it happy. If God ſhould
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103781:6"/> give us <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>fleſh from Heaven,</hi> and be always working miracles for us, a murmuring and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Spirit would ſtill make us miſerable. The bondage of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and a deliverance from it, would be equally grievous and uneaſy to it. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Oppreſſion, Sedition and Rebellion, Schiſm and Faction, are the names of great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as well as of great Sins. Senſuality trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth Men into the likeneſs of Beaſts, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and malice of Devils: and what a wretched Society muſt ſuch people make? Can a People be happy, where they are continually envying and vexing, cheating and defrauding, cenſuring and reviling, ſtriving and quarrelling with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>where judgment is turned away backward, and juſtice ſtandeth afar off, where truth is fallen in the ſtreet, and equity cannot enter?</hi> Is not this the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a very unhappy, as well as of a very wicked People? We can hardly mention any ſin, but the common and conſtant practice of it, is not only likely to procure, but is it ſelf a great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon a Nation. It is therefore mentioned as a heavy curſe upon <hi>Iſrael, Pſ.</hi> 81. 12. that <hi>God gave them up to their own hearts luſts; and they walked in their own counſels. Oh that I had in the wilderneſs,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, a lodging place of wayfaring men, that I might leave my people and go from them: for they be all adulterers, an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103781:6"/> of treacherous men.</hi> Jer. 9. 2. <hi>David</hi> alſo maketh the ſame wiſh, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55. when he ſaw <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and ſtrife in the City, deceit and guile in her ſtreets.</hi> The deſolation and barrenneſs of a <hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> were a deſirable refuge, from the greater ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of theſe ſins.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Sin doth farther tend to make a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unhappy, by the natural fruits and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it. Is it not vice and paſſion that break the bands of love and concord, the moſt neceſſary preſervatives of publick happineſs? <hi>From whence come wars and fightings among you? come they not hence, of your luſts that war in your members? Jam.</hi> 4. 1. It is our <hi>Saviours</hi> own obſervation; That <hi>a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi> And from whence is it, that a Church or Kingdom is divided into Sects and Factions, that ſome are of <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſome of <hi>Apollos;</hi> is it not becauſe they <hi>are carnal?</hi> Are not combuſtions of States and Kingdoms, and all unhappy broils, the natural fruits of pride and ambition? <hi>He that is of a proud heart ſtirreth up ſtrife,</hi> and <hi>Only by pride,</hi> ſaith So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, <hi>cometh contention Prov.</hi> 28. 25. 13. 10: Is it not natural for proud and ambitious ſpirits to do all they can to unſettle that Government, which doth not advance them according to their opinion of their own merits; and to try by repeated changes and revolutions, to raiſe themſelves to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103781:7"/> their affected greatneſs? <hi>The love of money is the root of all evil,</hi> from whence thoſe evil practiſes do naturally ſpring, which are continually diſturbing the world, waſting and ſpoiling, confounding and ruining, the Nations of it: Idleneſs and Luxury impoveriſh a Nation, and make it unable to bear the charge of its own defence: Senſuality impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the underſtanding, and enfeebleth the ſpirits of men, and maketh them unfit for counſel or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it taketh them off from all concern for the common good, and from all other care, but for their own eaſe and pleaſure; and maketh them unwilling to part with any, for the Publick ſafety, for fear they ſhould want it to <hi>conſume upon their luſts:</hi> Irreligion and Prophaneſs diſſolve the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt obligation, which is that of Conſcience, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to obſerve thoſe Laws, upon which all So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties are founded and ſubſiſt. And if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity ſuffer, through the raſhneſs or negligence, the unfaithfulneſs or treachery, of riotous, and lewd, and Atheiſtical men, intruſted to manage the affairs of it; no one can think any ſtrange thing hath happened. It would be very eaſy to ſhew, of all particular ſins and vices, that they have a very ill influence upon Societies, and do faturally tend to the great damage and diſſolution on them. Certainly then the condition of a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people muſt needs be moſt deſperate, when they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103781:7"/> have nothing elſe to ſecure them from Miſery and Deſtruction, but an extraordinary interpoſal of the Divine power and providence. For can we imagine that God will always work miracles on the behalf of his enemies? and alter the natural tendency of things, meerly that the wicked may go unpuniſhed? Will he ſtill refuſe to avenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when nothing more ſhall be required towards it, but to ſtand ſtill and ſuffer <hi>wickedneſs to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ſinner?</hi> On the contrary</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We have abundant reaſon to conclude, that the providence of God will farther promote the unhappineſs of a wicked people, and manifeſt it ſelf in ſevere and ſignal judgments upon them. For</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Honour of God is very much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it. When a People have generally <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted their ways;</hi> when they that can hardly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in any thing elſe, can yet unanimouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, to break the Laws, and dare the Power and Juſtice of God; if he ſhould ſtill <hi>keep ſilence,</hi> if ſuch publick affronts, ſuch combinations of Sinners do not move him to the execution of judgment upon them: Men will be ready to conclude with thoſe <hi>Zeph. 1. 12. That God doth neither good nor evil.</hi> He is therefore concerned for the honour of his providence, to convince the world, that <hi>he is a God that judgeth in the Earth,</hi> and <hi>governeth the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103781:8"/> Nations of it,</hi> to ariſe and <hi>viſit for theſe things, and to avenge himſelf on ſuch a Nation as this.</hi> Upon occaſion of ſuch high and notorious provocations, ſuch a general defection from God, even good men are ready to expoſtulate with him, in the Language of <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> and <hi>David; O our God wilt thou not judge them? How long ſhall the wicked, how long ſhall the wicked triumph?</hi> And then, if ever, it ſeemeth neceſſary, for the <hi>God to whom vengeance belongeth to ſhew himſelf,</hi> and to make his power and juſtice <hi>known, by the judgments that he executeth.</hi> Theſe National judgments, are ſuch publick manifeſtations of the Providence and Juſtice of God, as all the Neighbouring Countries can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve; they are warnings and examples to all the World, teaching <hi>all men to fear,</hi> proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the name of God to all the ends of the earth, and cauſing it to be <hi>ſaid among the Nations, the Lord reigneth.</hi> And therefore there is abundant rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to expect them from a God that is ſo highly concerned for the honour of his great name.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God hath expreſly declared, that his Providence ſhall interpoſe in promoting the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or miſery of a People, according to their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: That this is the courſe, he is reſolved to take with the Nations of the earth, <hi>to pull down, or to build up,</hi> according as they perſiſt in, or turn from their evil ways. <hi>Jer 18. 7, 8, 9, 10. At what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103781:8"/> I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Kingdom, to pluck up, and to pull down, and to deſtroy it: If that Nation againſt whom I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, turn from their evil: I will repent of the evil I thought to do unto them. And at what inſtant, I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation, and concerning a Kingdom, to build and to plant it: If it do evil in my ſight, that it obey not my voice, then will I repent of the good, wherewith I ſaid I would benefit them. The Lord hath a controverſy with the Nations: He will plead with all fleſh, he will give them that are wicked to the ſword, ſaith the Lord. Jer.</hi> 25. 31. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly we find</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That the Providence of God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways interpoſed in this manner, that in all ages his judgments have followed the prevailing wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Church or Nation. When God <hi>ſaw that the wickedneſs of man was great,</hi> and that <hi>all fleſh had corrupted his way upon the earth,</hi> he ſent an overwhelming deluge, to cleanſe it of its corrupt inhabitants. And by <hi>fire and brimſtone from heaven,</hi> conſumed the proud and luſtful Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha.</hi> What a ſucceſſion of dreadful plagues, did God ſend on the oppreſſing <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans?</hi> And what terrible deſtruction was made of the <hi>Amorites, and all the Kingdoms of Canaan,</hi> when at length their <hi>iniquities were become full?</hi> And all along the Old Teſtament, we find the judgments
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103781:9"/> of God, Famine or Peſtilence, Captivity or the Sword, continually following the growing wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of his People <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And when at length they had <hi>killed the Prophets, and ſtoned them that were ſent unto them;</hi> when they would not hearken to the gracious invitations of the Bleſſed Jeſus, and the Son of God himſelf could not perſwade them to repent, the Lord brought their greateſt fears upon them; <hi>The Romans came and took away their place and and Nation.</hi> And when the conquering <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves, had laid aſide that temperance and juſtice, by which they had been raiſed; and to their other abominable ſins had ſuperadded their Blaſphemies againſt God, and moſt barbarous vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and cruelty to his people, erecting pillars to their Emperors, as Trophies of their aboliſhing Chriſtianity: Then did the Providence of God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt it ſelf in many ſevere and ſignal judgments upon them. In the reign of one Emperor; there was in <hi>Rome</hi> a moſt raging Famine; a Plague, of which, we are told, there dyed in that City 2000 a day: Great multitudes were ſlain in a Sedition; and a great part of the wealth of the City was conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Fire from Heaven. And beſides theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Commodus,</hi> there were many of the like Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments under their following Emperors until <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</hi> And when the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Emperor at length fell into all manner of Vice and Wickedneſs, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103781:9"/> 
               <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> and other rude and barbarous Nations, were let looſe upon it, and ſuddenly made moſt terrible havock and deſtruction of it. But we need not ſearch into Ancient, or Foreign Chronicles, for inſtances of the wrath of God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the ſins of a provoking people. For if a long and bloody War amongſt our ſelves, and all the woful effects of it; a waſting and devouring Plague, and moſt dreadful and conſuming Fires, may be reckoned as publick Judgments; the ſins of this Age and Nation have not altogether gone unpuniſhed. This then hath manifeſtly been the conſtant courſe of Gods providence, to ſhowre down his Judgments on a ſinful people. And that we may rationally conclude from hence, that it will be ſo ſtill, will appear, if we conſider theſe <hi>two</hi> things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That God is the ſame Wiſe, and Juſt, and Holy God, and Governour of the world that ever he was. He is <hi>the Lord that changes not;</hi> and <hi>his Dominion endureth throughout all Generations. Are not</hi> his <hi>ways</hi> ſtill <hi>equal? Will not the Judge of all the world</hi> ſtill <hi>do right?</hi> Is not his hatred of ſin as great as ever? and his inclination to puniſh it? Doth he repent of his paſt ſeverity, or find cauſe to correct the wonted method of his providence? Doth not <hi>the Lord ſtill ſee, or hath he forſaken the earth?</hi> If God be ſtill <hi>the Governour among the Nations;</hi> If
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103781:10"/> his providence be ſtill directed by the ſame wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and holineſs, and juſtice, we may ſafely conclude, that his dealing with ſinful nations, as to the ſubſtance of it, will be the ſame too? that becauſe he hath not, therefore he will not, finally acquit a wicked and impenitent people; but ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or later, as he hath always done, will <hi>viſit their iniquities with Rods, and their ſins with Scourges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Spirit of God in Scripture doth uſe this very way of arguing from former exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods judgments. <hi>Jer. 25. 29. God doth thus reaſon with the Nations. He telleth them, they ſhall drink the cup of his Fury: For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Lo, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to bring evil on the City which is called by my name, and ſhould ye be utterly unpuniſhed?</hi> Do I puniſh them for their iniquities, and ſhall I not puniſh you for yours? <hi>ye ſhall not be unpuniſhed; for I will call for a Sword upon all the inhabitants of the earth, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> After the ſame manner doth St. <hi>Peter</hi> argue, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. and the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verſes. <hi>If God ſpared not the old world, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the flood upon the world of the ungodly; And turned the Cities of Sodom and Gomorrha into aſhes,</hi> he inferreth, That <hi>the Lord ſtill knoweth how,</hi> that is, is ſtill able and ready, <hi>to reſerve the unjuſt unto the day of judgment to be puniſhed;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, To reſerve the unjuſt <hi>being puniſhed</hi> here, in ſome ſuch remarkable manner,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103781:10"/> as the Old World, <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> were, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the day of Judgment, when they ſhall receive their eternal doom and recompence. St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 11th to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſheweth the danger the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians were in, from Gods ſeverity on the unbelieving <hi>Jews. Becauſe of unbelief they were broken off; be not high-minded but fear. For if God ſpared not the natural branches, take heed leſt he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſpare not thee. Rom.</hi> 11. 20, 21. He telleth us alſo plainly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 11. That the judgments which God ſent upon the Jews in the Wilderneſs, <hi>happened unto them for examples, and are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi> To teach all Nations, to the end of the world, to expect the like Judgments if they are ſinners like them. If the caſe then of a ſinful people be thus deſperate, if prevailing wickedneſs will thus certainly make them unhappy; not only by it ſelf, and the fruits that naturally ſpring from it; but alſo by provoking the wrath and pulling down the judgments of God upon them; Doth it not greatly behove us in time to look about us, and to ſee whether the clouds be not gathering, and the wrath of God ready to fall in moſt horrible tempeſts upon us? I come therefore</p>
            <p>Secondly, To ſhew, That we of this Nation are very much concerned, in the truth of the Propoſition I have been now proving, and that it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103781:11"/> 
               <hi>propheſieth evil concerning us.</hi> This will be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently manifeſt, if we do but <hi>ſearch and try our ways,</hi> and impartially conſider what great ſinners we are. A meditation very proper and ſeaſonable at this time, now that we are met together <hi>to call our ſins to remembrance,</hi> and to humble our ſelves for them. Give me leave therefore, to <hi>ſet</hi> ſome of them <hi>in order before you,</hi> and briefly to repreſent the ſinful ſtate and condition of this our Nation.</p>
            <p>And here I am entring upon a ſubject, will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us equal matter, both of wonder and of grief; of wonder, that there ſhould be ſuch and ſo much wickedneſs practiſed, where ſo pure and holy a Religion is profeſſed; and of grief too, that we ſhould be theſe Offenders, and <hi>Englands</hi> ſins the matter of our aſtoniſhment. If a man ſhould bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemplate the purity of our Religion, and the great ſtir we make about it, with what heat and zeal we contend about ſome little matters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to it, he might with reaſon enough con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that we were the moſt religious and holy people upon earth: But if he come once abroad, and look but with half an eye upon the lives and common practices of men amongſt us, he would ſoon find he was miſtaken in his concluſion, and that the moſt zealous pretenders to the moſt pure and holy Religion, may be as corrupt and wicked, as thoſe that have <hi>no</hi> true <hi>knowledge of God in their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103781:11"/> Land.</hi> Are not Atheiſm and Infidelity openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed by our Heroick Sinners, and ſome pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Refiners of Wit and Reaſon amongſt us? Who, if they will allow <hi>him</hi> to be a <hi>Fool</hi> that <hi>ſaith in his heart there is no God,</hi> it is becauſe he ſaith it only <hi>in his heart,</hi> and declareth it not with them in more publick and daring expreſſions. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that <hi>profeſs to know God,</hi> how many <hi>in works deny him, being abominable, and diſobedient, and to every good work reprobate?</hi> Blaſphemies, Oaths, and Curſes ſeem to be affected, as the greateſt Ornaments of Speech; in which men are as loud, as <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts were in their Prayers, and repeat them as often too, as if like them they were afraid leſt God ſhould not hear; leſt <hi>judgment ſhould ſleep, or their damnation ſlumber.</hi> How many ſuch <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> have we of whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> could not ſpeak without <hi>weeping; whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is in their ſhame, who</hi> inordinately <hi>mind earthly things? Rioting and Drunkenneſs, Chambering and Wantonneſs,</hi> are ſuch general and publick vices, that they can hardly now be called the <hi>works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> not that they better become the light now than formerly, but thoſe that commit them are leſs afraid of it: Fraud and cozening, lying and injuſtice, are the common methods of purſuing the profits of this world; and hardly ever any age was better skilled, or more practiſed, in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103781:12"/> arts of cheating and over-reaching one another. Where is that undiſſembled and hearty love, which our Lord hath made the principal badge and cognizance of his Diſciples? How are we eſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and divided from one another? And how jealous of all attempts for the uniting and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling of us? How uncharitable are we in our cenſures, how bitter in our revilings, how merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and revengeful in our behaviour one towards another? How is every thing that is Sacred pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned by us? How great and ſcandalous are our neglects, how irreverent and hypocritical our performances of the duties of Gods worſhip? How full of iniquity our moſt holy things? I have not time to be more particular; we are thus, and much more ſinful, after all the various methods of heaven to reform us. <hi>What could God have done more to his Vineyard, that he hath not done in it?</hi> We have had <hi>line upon line, and precept upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept?</hi> the brighteſt diſcoveries of our duty, and moſt frequent and earneſt invitations to perform it: But all this while God hath <hi>ſtretched forth his hands to a diſobedient and gainſaying people.</hi> God hath placed us in a fruitful and pleaſant Land, and <hi>given us all things richly to enjoy.</hi> We have had <hi>peace within our Walls, no leading into Captivity, no</hi> juſt <hi>complaining in our ſtreets;</hi> but have lived in eaſe and quiet, whilſt almoſt every corner of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103781:12"/> World beſide, hath been filled with violence, and rapine, and blood. How many, and how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful have our deliverances been, from the ſecret conſpiracies and the open violence of our <hi>Romiſh</hi> Adverſaries? Yea <hi>what Nation is there that hath had God ſo nigh unto them, for all we could call upon him for?</hi> But ſo prodigious hath been our Ingratitude, that we have fruſtrated the deſign of all this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which ſhould have led us to repentance, and the ſtrongeſt <hi>Cords of</hi> the divine <hi>Love</hi> have been too weak to <hi>draw</hi> us to our God; as if we had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to outdo the miracles of his mercy, by a more miraculous Ingratitude. <hi>Thus have we requited the Lord, O fooliſh people and unwiſe!</hi> God hath ſometimes uſed ſeverer methods with us and ſent <hi>his judgments into our land,</hi> that from thence <hi>the inhabitants might learn righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> But we have multiplied our tranſgreſſions whilſt his Rod hath been upon our backs, and <hi>in the time of our diſtreſs have ſinned yet more againſt him.</hi> God hath <hi>ſtricken us,</hi> but we have <hi>revolted more and more,</hi> and have come out of the fire but more hardned and more unmalleable. If all this then be a true, though not a full account of our wicked ſtate, as I would to God it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to prove the contrary, certainly put all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it will make up the character of a moſt Prodigiouſly wicked, ungrateful and incorrigible
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103781:13"/> People. What abundant reaſon then have we to conclude, notwithſtanding all <hi>the great things God hath</hi> lately <hi>done for us,</hi> and the moſt hopeful ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances we now have, that <hi>for all this his anger is not turned away from us, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill;</hi> and that er'e long, if we take not due and timely care to prevent it, we may to our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion, experience what a <hi>fearful thing it is to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi> Methinks now the conſideration of that ſad and terrible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode our ſins do make, that <hi>fearful looking for of judgment and fiery indignation to devour us,</hi> they ſo juſtly call for, ſhould <hi>prick us all to the heart,</hi> and make us ready to cry out with St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Acts. 2. Men and Brethren what ſhall we do? What ſhall we do to be ſaved</hi> from theſe Calamities, to <hi>fly from this Wrath to come?</hi> If this now be the Frame and Language of our Souls, then are we rightly diſpoſed, as they were, to hear our duty; and I would to God it might be with as good ſucceſs. And thus I come to the next thing I am to do, which is</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To ſhew what is to be done by us, for the preventing that evil our ſins threatens us with.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We ſhould humble our ſelves before God, and <hi>ſigh and cry for the abominations are done in the midſt of us.</hi> But Oh! what ſighs, what ſorrow,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103781:13"/> can be great or loud enough for us? For us, who are not only to bewail the ſins of ſome few parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, but of a whole <hi>land that lieth in wickedneſs;</hi> not only ſome of the loweſt rank, but the higheſt and moſt provoking abominations? Certainly never any had greater reaſon than we have at this day, to break out into that paſſionate wiſh of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, Oh that our heads were waters, and our eyes fountains of tears, that we might weep day and night: Becauſe of the wickedneſs we have committed to provoke the Lord to anger.</hi> Did our Bleſſed Lord weep over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that ungrateful City, when he conſidered the greatneſs of her ſins, and the nearneſs of her deſtruction; though he was himſelf without ſin, and no ways acceſſary to the provoking that wrath was coming upon them? And can we look with dry eyes and unaffected hearts, on thoſe numerous tranſgreſſions we have all a ſhare in, on thoſe future judgments we have ſo much reaſon to fear, and the beſt of us all have helped to deſerve? God forbid we ſhould be thus inſenſible! O let us in time, we pretend to do it at this time, <hi>humble our ſelves and God will exalt us;</hi> Let us <hi>mourn and God will comfort us; He will give us beauty for aſhes, the oyl of joy for mourning, and the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſs;</hi> Let us offer unto God the <hi>Sacrifices of broken and contrite hearts,</hi> and the <hi>High and lofty One will dwell with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103781:14"/> us, revive and comfort us;</hi> Let us <hi>turn to him with weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and faſting and mourning, and even rent our hearts before him;</hi> for <hi>then,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Joel, Chap. 2. The Lord will be jealous for his people, and pity his land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, To our ſorrow and humiliation let us joyn our prayers, implore his pardon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precate the wrath of God. Let us take with us words, and turn to the Lord, and ſay unto him, Take away all our iniquities and receive us graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; Let us beſeech him with all that affection and importunity, which becometh the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the ſuit, <hi>not to remember our offences, not to take vengeance of our ſins, but to ſpare his people whom he hath redeemed.</hi> Hearty and fervent Prayer hath a mighty prevailing power with God: The greateſt bleſſings are promiſed to it, and the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt things have been effected by it: It hath open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſhut the <hi>windows of heaven,</hi> and reſtored departed ſouls to their forſaken bodies: It defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the malice of <hi>Haman,</hi> the wiſdom and counſel of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> and put to flight an army of a thouſand thouſand <hi>Ethiopians:</hi> It hath prevailed with God to revoke the judgments he hath denounced, and to deliver his people after he had declared he would <hi>deliver them no more.</hi> How then ſhould this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us <hi>to lift up our hearts with our hands to God in the heavens;</hi> to embrace all opportunities of pouring out our ſupplications before him, both
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103781:14"/> in our <hi>cloſets,</hi> and our <hi>houſes of prayer?</hi> To <hi>pray without ceaſing,</hi> with the utmoſt vigour of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; To <hi>cry mightily unto God,</hi> to <hi>wreſtle</hi> and not give over, till with <hi>Jacob</hi> we have <hi>prevailed,</hi> prevailed with God and obtained his <hi>bleſſing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, We muſt add the reformation and amendment of our lives. Otherwiſe our Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation will be mockery, and our Prayer ſin. Our ſins are the <hi>Achans, the troublers of Iſrael;</hi> and were but theſe <hi>accurſed things put away from amongſt us,</hi> we might then be confident, that God would be appeaſed and the Nation flouriſh. It is <hi>to the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> only that <hi>God ſaith there is no peace. But the work of righteouſneſs, is peace, and the effect of Righteouſneſs, quietneſs and aſſurance for ever.</hi> O then that we would all <hi>know, that in this our day we would know the things that belong unto our peace:</hi> That every one of us would bid an eternal farewel to his ſins, in that paſſionate ſtile of returning <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim; What have we to do any more with</hi> you? Hence ye diſturbers of our peace, ye provokers of our God, and moſt treacherous underminers of the ſafety and happineſs, both of Church and State. Let us then reſolve, and if we do it not we have but diſſembled with God in our approaches this day, Let us reſolve henceforward to ingage with all our might, in bridling our paſſions, in curbing our appetites, in mortifying our luſts, in <hi>pulling
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103781:15"/> down the ſtrong holds of Satan in us,</hi> and in <hi>bringing nto captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> And thus <hi>fighting the good fight of Faith,</hi> we may as effectually promote, the ſafety and honour of our Country, as if we had ſerved in its Fleets or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. This is the way to ſtrengthen the hands of them that fight for us, to ſend them moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al relief and ſuccour, to bring down the <hi>Lord of hoſts to go before them, the God of Iſrael to be their Rereward, to be a wall of fire round about them; and the glory in the midſt both of them and us. O that my people had hearkened unto me,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>and Iſrael had walked in my ways: I ſhould ſoon have ſubdued their enemies, and turned my hand againſt their adverſaries. Pſ.</hi> 81. 13, 14.</p>
            <p>But is it not, may ſome object, an univerſal Reformation that muſt produce theſe happy effects? To what purpoſe then will our perſonal and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Reformation ſerve? For the anſwering of this I ſhall proceed to the laſt thing I am to do, which is</p>
            <p>Fourthly, To endeavour by ſome proper mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to perſwade every one to do his own part in that; the general practice whereof is the only cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain means, to procure the favour and divert the judgments of God. To this end therefore let us conſider theſe following things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That a General Reformation is nothing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103781:15"/> elſe, but the Reformation of all Particulars, and if ever it be wrought amongſt us, it muſt be the work of particular perſons, and the reſult of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one's doing his own part. Let us not then ſtay for examples, but rather contend for the honour of being examples to others. Let us ſtrive who ſhall be firſt, and moſt active, in ſo noble a deſign, in ſetting forward that work, wherein the Honour and Happineſs of our Country is ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. How great an influence might your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples have upon this whole City? And how ſoon do the manners and faſhions of that overſpread the Nation? You are therefore more concerned than others to begin this great and bleſſed work; to cauſe your <hi>light ſo to ſhine before,</hi> and above other <hi>men, that ſeeing your good works, they may</hi> be won by the charms of a bright and illuſtrious vertue, to follow your ſteps, and to <hi>glorify your Father which is in heaven.</hi> And this would advance your reputation, and perpetuate your memories more than all the dignities of this world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Though by doing our own parts, we ſhould not be able to do much towards a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Reformation, yet we might make up ſuch a number, for whoſe ſake God might ſpare and bleſs the whole Land. How ready was God to have ſpared even <hi>Sodom</hi> it ſelf, had there been but <hi>ten righteous</hi> perſons <hi>found in it.</hi> He did ſpare the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103781:16"/> City <hi>Zoar</hi> for the ſake of <hi>Lot</hi> and the ſmall compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with him. A ſingle act of one ſingle man ſtaid the fury of a devouring Plague, and reſtored <hi>health to the Congregation of Iſrael. Pſ. 106. 30. Then ſtood up Phinehas, and executed judgment; and ſo the plague was ſtayed.</hi> To which I may add that gracious Proclamation we find publiſhed <hi>Jer. 5. 1. Run ye to and fro through the ſtreets of Jeruſalem, and ſee now and know, and ſeek in the broad places thereof, if ye can find a man, if there be any that executeth judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſeeketh the truth, and I will pardon it.</hi> One faithful Magiſtrate executing Judgment had ſaved that great City. How then ſhould this encourage <hi>you</hi> to a zealous and upright execution of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution ye have made, Not to <hi>bear the Sword in vain, but to make it a terrour to evil-doers:</hi> Thus avowedly to ſet your ſelves to <hi>deſtroy the works of the Devil:</hi> To be hearty and couragious in the cauſe of God and righteouſneſs, <hi>in the midſt of ſo crooked and perverſe a Nation;</hi> To contemn all the cenſures and reproaches the execution of juſtice and judgment may expoſe you to? Who knoweth how far this might prevail with God? If a few righteous men can yet ſave us, none ſo likely to do it, as ſuch Magiſtrates, by ſuch heroick piety and vertue. There may be a time indeed when the ſins of a Nation are ſo ripe, that <hi>though Noah, Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and Job were in it,</hi> they could not avert the judgments of God, yet conſider
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103781:16"/> Thirdly, That however <hi>They may deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their righteouſneſs.</hi> Our perſonal reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may procure a refuge for us in the day of Gods wrath. Thus <hi>Noah</hi> eſcaped the Deluge of waters, and <hi>Lot</hi> the flames of <hi>Sodom;</hi> and <hi>thoſe that ſighed and cried for the abominations of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the fury of that deſtroying <hi>Angel, who went through the midſt of it.</hi> In what manner God doth often deal with good men, when his judgments are abroad in the earth, we have at large deſcribed in <hi>Pſ. 91. Thou ſhalt not be afraid of the terrour by night, nor for the arrow that flyeth by day; nor for the peſtilence that walketh in darkneſs nor for the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that waſteth at noon day. A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand: but it ſhall not come nigh thee.</hi> If notwithſtanding it ſhould ſeem good to the Divine Wiſdom to involve us in the common calamity, yet let us conſider</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That the conſcience of our own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal reformation would be then a moſt comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſupport to us. What a reviving conſideration would it be, when the judgments of God are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, that we are not the guilty cauſes of them; that we have done our parts to prevent them, and and are clear from the blood of all men? That even theſe things <hi>will work together for our good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we love God and keep his Commandments;</hi> That all theſe clouds cannot intercept the <hi>light of Gods countenance, or hide his face</hi> or favour <hi>from us:</hi> that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103781:17"/> 
               <hi>no tribulation or diſtreſs; neiter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, nor nakedneſs, nor peril, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> able to ſeparate us from the Love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Conſider how unſucceſsful ſoever our perſonal reformation may be in promoting the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, or our own particular good here; it will not fail of a great and glorious reward hereafter. <hi>For ſo an entrance ſhall be adminiſtred unto us into that City, which hath Foundations, whoſe builder and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker is God, into the everlaſting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Where we ſhall be free from ſin, and all the dreadful conſequences of it: and when not only the Cities and Nations of this world, but this world and time it ſelf ſhall be no more, we ſhall be ſtill ſecure in the enjoyment of the moſt perfect peace and happineſs. To conclude then, I exhort and beſeech you all, as you regard the Honour and Preſervation of your Country, your own preſent Good and Safety, and the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs of the Life to come; by all that is valuable and dear to you, both in this and the other world; that you would no longer delay that Reformation, in which all theſe things are ſo highly concerned. <hi>O that there were ſuch an heart in every one of us, to repent and turn from all our tranſgreſſions, to fear God, and to keep his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments always, that it might be well with us and with our children for ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103781:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
